ASSOCIATE RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Professional Summary

Ambitious Research Scientist with track record of dependability and leadership. Knowledgeable in QA methodology with proven history of reducing errors to increase quality. Proficient in preparing test cases, plans and scripts. Dedicated to analyzing and resolving defects. Personable Analyst with excellent computer system quality analysis experience. Talented at interpreting complex data, analyzing test procedure improvements and investigating product and service failures. Skilled critical thinker with expansive mathematical abilities.

Skills

- Documentation expertise and File management
- Experiment Design
- Method validation and Analytical Methodology Validation
- Clinical assays, Spectroscopic analysis, Data analysis
- Good Laboratory Practices (GLP)
- MS Office

- Organization and Time Management
- Test Results Interpretation and Critical Thinking
- Problem Solving and Solution Development and Optimization
- Quality SOPs Development and Quality Control Data Compilation
- LabWare LIMS and Practiced in Empower
- New Product Development

Work History

Associate Research Scientist Dow Chemical Company - South Charleston, WV 03/2021 - Current

- Performed research into study topics to increase knowledge and to provide valuable contributions.
- Wrote reports, reviews and summaries regarding method developments, process validations, method validations.
- Conducted studies to develop responsible strategies for use of drugs, disposal of waste along with addiction studies.
- Evaluated test results for completeness and accuracy, submitting results to quality assurance personnel.
- Generated data models, performed required analysis and helped produce reports outlining results.
- Performed validation procedures for testing and analysis on commercial products and obtained required data sets.
- Maintained confidentiality of all information to conform to FDA, internal and other regulatory standards.
- Documented and reported test results after making graphical solutions and representations.
- Used Empower and chemstation to determine data-set correlations while initiating qualitative functions.
- Recognized abnormal test results and devised corrective actions to retain accurate and valid results.
- Collaborated with leadership team to identify relevant questions and determine best methods of collection.
- Streamlined research processes to meet tight deadlines for multiple projects.
- Conducted stability studies on raw material along with finished products in drug development.
- Conducted Assays, related compounds and stability tests regularly.
- Improved operations through consistent hard work and dedication.
- Adhered to social distancing protocols and wore mask or face shield.
- Operated specialized scientific equipment and performed complex procedures to execute high-level analytical testing tasks.
- Advised chemists and laboratory technicians on existing and emerging quality control methods to enhance testing and research capabilities.
- Developed new analytical techniques and enhanced existing analytical methods to improve testing validity and applicability.
- Collaborated with laboratory technicians, production personnel and customers to improve product quality and functionality.
- Participated in new process development and process optimization programs to enhance overall system capabilities.
- Prepared and standardized test equipment, test solutions and reagents to enable successful testing completion.
- Carefully handled lab samples and disposed of waste by adhering to safety protocols.
- Performed preventive maintenance and calibrated equipment to keep laboratory in compliance with FDA standards.
- Modified and adapted standard methods and procedures to solve analytical problems.
- Performed technical laboratory functions in compliance with regulatory agencies and safety requirements.
- Cleaned and organized laboratory and kept supplies well-stocked to save time, money and promote laboratory efficiency.
- Assisted with collecting, identifying and packaging hazardous and non-hazardous waste products to comply with Resource Conservation and Recovery Act regulations.
- Performed standardized tests on organic and inorganic compounds to observe fundamental differences in properties.
- Conducted more than 50 studies on process validations for each drug product.

Clinical Pharmacologist Intern Pacific Premier Bank - Dallas , TX 05/2020 - 08/2020

- Developed knowledge about biopharmaceuticals and clinical pharmacology geared towards clinical development of new drugs
- Correlating translational science and clinical pharmacology in drug development process
- Conduct literature reviews as needed for interpretation of study data and development of next steps
- Experienced to lead clinical study protocol development process by translating strategy and approved concept into executable, efficient clinical protocols, and related documents
- Identifying study issues and program issues by reviewing and monitoring of emerging clinical data related to safety, efficacy, and PK/PD by developing sound, strategic solutions to issues and collaborates with clinical study team to ensure issue resolution
- Supported development of program documents
- Provided therapy incorporating cognitive-behavioral, client-centered and play-therapy to treat wide range of neurological problems in natients.
- Consulted with and trained highly skilled mental health and medical staff.
- Scheduled, organized and delivered comprehensive presentations on effective treatment of depression, anxiety, anger and cognitivebehavioral skills to manage negative emotions.

Summer Intern Public Testing Laboratory - City, STATE 08/2017 - 10/2017

- Calibrated and maintained laboratory spectrometers and chromatographs.
- Created spreadsheets and other forms of documentation to accurately record and calculate analytical results.
- Resolved routine issues and escalated non-standard or critical issues to Quality Assurance department for corrective action.
- Contributed to team discussions and new project initiatives to advance progress and optimize profitability.
- Coordinated and performed analytical tests to comply with established standards and specifications.
- Created and optimized records management strategies to coordinate and protect information.
- Produced high-quality documents, spreadsheets and presentations for internal and customer-facing needs.
- Sorted and organized files, spreadsheets and reports.
- Opened, sorted and distributed incoming mail and packages.

Education

Master of Science: Pharmaceutics, Industrial Pharmacy Long Island University - City 01/2021

- Professional development completed in Industrial Pharmacy.
- Relevant Coursework Completed: Regulatory Affairs, Pharmaceutical Analysis.
- Relevant Coursework Completed: Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics PBPK- Modelling and Simulation (SIMCYP, PHEONIX WINNONLIN),
- Relevant Coursework Completed: Regulatory Overview

Bachelor of Pharmacy: Pharmacy, Pharmaceutical Sciences and Technology Poona College of Pharmacy - City 06/2018

- Continuing education in Pharmaceutical Sciences
- Relevant Coursework Completed: Medicinal Chemistry Pharmacology Biopharmaceutics Regulatory sciences

Languages Hindi:

Full Professional

Hindi:

Full Professional